<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the Lords and Commons for the repayment of 40000 li. (out of the first moneys raised upon the weekly assesssment) which the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of London have engaged themselves forthwith to advance for the supply of the Army under the command of his excellency the Earl of Essex. Die Mercurii, 5. Aprol, 1643.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02980</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1429B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R176109</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52529149</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52529149</idno>
            <idno type="VID">178781</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02980)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178781)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2770:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the Lords and Commons for the repayment of 40000 li. (out of the first moneys raised upon the weekly assesssment) which the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of London have engaged themselves forthwith to advance for the supply of the Army under the command of his excellency the Earl of Essex. Die Mercurii, 5. Aprol, 1643.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Initial letters.</note>
                  <note>Notes in ms. beneath documents.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>With: An ordinance of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, concerning 23000 li. lately lent by the Lord Mayor, Aldermen and Commons of London, to be repaid out of the debts and rents of houses gathered by the collectors, Die Sabbathi, 6. Maii, 1643.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Appropriations and expenditures --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Finance --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:178781:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
            <head>A Declaration of the Lords and Commons for the repayment of 40000 li. (out of the firſt moneys raiſed upon the weekly Aſſeſſement) which the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of <hi>London</hi> have engaged themſelves forthwith to advance for the ſupply of the Army under the command of his Excellency the Earl of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Mercurii, 5. April, 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas it was Ordained and declared upon the laſt day of <hi>February,</hi> 1642. by the Lords and Commons aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Parliament, that all perſons who had or ſhould lend any monies towards the ſpeedy making up of the ſum of threeſcore thouſand pounds then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, for the ſupply of the Army, ſhould be repayed the ſame with conſideration for the forbearance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, after the rate of eight pounds <hi>per Cent.</hi> out of the firſt monies to be raiſed out of the weekly Aſſeſſements by vertue of the late Ordinance of both Houſes of Parliament. And whereas the ſaid ſumme not being fully advanced, the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> upon the motion and deſires of divers Members of both Houſes of Parliament, did chearfully and unanimouſly conſent to engage themſelves for forty thouſand pounds, to be advanced forthwith for the ſupply of the ſaid Army raiſed by the Parliament, under the Command of his Excellency the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> which is, and is underſtood and taken to be a very acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable ſervice, eſpecially at this time, and tends very much to the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Religion, Lawes, and Liberties, and the ſafety of the Parliament City, and Kingdome; It is thereupon ordained and declared by the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, that as well the money already lent towards the ſaid threeſcore thouſand pounds, as alſo the ſaid forty thouſand pounds now to be advanced as aforeſaid, ſhall be repaid with conſideration for the forbearance thereof, after eight pounds <hi>per Cent.</hi> out of the firſt monies to be raiſed on the ſaid weekly Aſſeſſements. And for their further ſecurity and encouragement, it is likewiſe ordained and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that the weekly Aſſeſſements to be collected in <hi>London</hi> and the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, ſhall be paid to Sir <hi>John Wollaſton</hi> Knight, <hi>John Warner, John Towſe,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Andrewes,</hi> Aldermen, Treaſurers in <hi>Guild-Hall London;</hi> who are hereby directed and appointed to repay the ſummes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready lent and to be advanced as aforeſaid, according to the intent of this and the ſaid recited Ordinance. And that the ſaid Treaſurers ſhall not iſſue or pay forth any part of the ſaid monies, to be raiſed on the ſaid Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſements, for any other purpoſe, untill the ſaid ſummes lent and to be lent, and advanced, be fully ſatisfied with intereſt, as aforeſaid; excepting onely ſuch monies as are appointed for the uſe of the City, which is to be iſſued out by them, according to the ſaid Ordinance made for the weekly Aſſeſſements.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Browne, Cler. Parliamentor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <head>An Ordinance of the Lords and Commons aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Parliament, concerning 23000 li. lately lent by the Lord Mayor, Aldermen and Commons of <hi>London,</hi> to be repaid out of the Debts and Rents of Houſes gathered by the Collectors.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Sabbathi, 6. Maii, 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas upon a motion made by a Committee of Lords and Commons, in the name of both Houſes of Parliament, for the ſum of threeſcore thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds to be advanced by the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> for ſupply of the neceſſities of the Army, the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and divers of the Commons of the ſaid City by vertue of an Ordinance of the 28. of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi> laſt did advance 23000 li. or thereabouts, which by another Ordinance of the 5. of <hi>April</hi> was to be repaid together with 40000 li. more, or thereabouts, lent and advanced by the Lord Mayor and Aldermen alone, with conſideration for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance thereof after the rate of 8. <hi>per centum per annum</hi> for the ſame, out of the firſt monies to be raiſed by the weekly Aſſeſſement in the City of <hi>London</hi> and Liberties thereof.</p>
            <p>And whereas the ſaid Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Commons, are contented that the firſt three and twenty thouſand pounds that ſhall be repaid out of the weekly Aſſeſſements, ſhall be ſet apart to be forthwith ſent to the Army to ſupply the preſent preſſing neceſſities thereof, and to be repaid the ſame after the ſaid 40000 li. with the forbearance thereof, as aforeſaid, is fully ſatisfied: And whereas the Commons of <hi>London,</hi> in Common-Councel aſſembled, have undertaken to doe their utmoſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to advance and lend 17000 li. to be forthwith alſo ſent unto the Army, to be repaid with the 23000 li. as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>All which advance of moneys is underſtood and taken to be a very acceptable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and tends very much to the preſervation of Religion, Laws and Liberties, and the ſafety of the Parliament, City, and Kingdome. It is therefore ordained and declared by the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, that as well the ſaid 23000 li. as alſo ſuch other moneys as ſhall be advanced as aforeſaid, ſhall be repaid with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration for the forbearance thereof, after the rate as aforeſaid, out of the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys to be raiſed upon the weekly Aſſeſſement, to be collected in <hi>London</hi> and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, after the 40000 li. lent and advanced by the Lord Mayor and Aldermen is fully ſatisfied as aforeſaid, and out of the firſt money collected or to be collected out of the weekly Aſſeſſements in the City of <hi>Weſtminiſter,</hi> the Borough of <hi>Southwark,</hi> the ſeveral Pariſhes in the weekly Bills, and in the reſt of the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> as alſo in the Counties of <hi>Hertford, Eſſex</hi> and <hi>Suffolk,</hi> as alſo out of the firſt moneys that ſhall be raiſed out of the Aſſeſſements of ſuch perſons throughout the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (not above the twentieth part of their eſtate, or the fifth part of their Annual revenue) as have not contributed upon the Propoſitions of both Houſes, or not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably to their Eſtates, according to an Ordinance of the  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
               </gap>  of <hi>May:</hi> And for their further ſecurity and encouragement, it is likewiſe ordained by the Lords and Commons aforeſaid, that as well Sir <hi>Gilbert Gerrard</hi> Baronet, Treaſurer of the Army, as alſo Sir <hi>John Wollaſton</hi> Knight, <hi>John Warner, John Towſe,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Andrewes,</hi> Aldermen of the City of <hi>London,</hi> appointed Treaſurers for the receipt of the ſaid moneys reſpectively, ſhall repay the ſaid ſeveral ſums as aforeſaid, and ſhall not iſſue the ſaid moneys to any other purpoſe whatſoever, untill the ſame ſhall be fully ſatisfied as aforeſaid. And it is further ordained, that ſuch ſums of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney as were advanced and not repaid, according to an Ordinance of the 29. of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> laſt, ſhall be repaid out of ſuch moneys as are or ſhall be raiſed by vertue of ſeveral Ordinances paſſed in and about the ſaid <hi>November,</hi> for aſſeſſing of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons within the City of <hi>London</hi> and Liberties thereof (not above the 20. part of their eſtates) as have not contributed upon the Propoſitions of hoth Houſes, or not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably to their eſtates, as alſo out of ſuch moneys as ſhall be raiſed by vertue of the aforeſaid Ordinance of the  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
               </gap>  of <hi>May</hi> aforeſaid.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
